Eugène Dettaa

University of Montreal, Department of Economics, 3150, Jean-Brillant street C-6070-5, Lionel Groulx Building, Montreal, QC, H3T 1N8, Canada +1 (514) 838-5676, eugene.delacroix.dettaa.mboudjiho@umontreal.ca

Summary

Insightful economist with an excellent academic background, I have more than four years of experience. My areas of expertise include theoretical and applied econometrics, in particular the use conventional econometric approaches, and their combination with machine learning methods, to assess causal effects, improve inference or prediction of economic variables. I have work experience in Cameroon and Canada which allowed me to develop skills in analyzing and modeling economic problems and using data to solve them. Whatever the task, I always perform it with great rigor, paying particular attention to every detail. It is always a real pleasure for me to put my knowledge at the service of society through the resolution of concrete problems.

Education	
Ph.D. Candidate in Economics, University of Montreal, Canada	2019-present
M.Sc. in Economics and Statistics, Sub-regional Institut of Statistics and Applied Economics (ISSEA), Cameroon	2016-2019
B.Sc. in Mathematics, University of Yaoundé I, Cameroon	2012-2015
Secondary and High School Teacher's Training Diploma, Higher Teachers' Training College of Yaoundé, Cameroon	2012-2016

Academic and professional experiences

Independent consultant

2018-present

- Discriminant analysis and neural networks for measuring the risk of non-execution of a project in the Public Investment Budget of Cameroon using administrative data, with Luc B. DIMAI, for ISSEA and MINEPAT (Cameroon), Fall and Winter 2018.
- VAR modeling to analyze the impact of public expenditure on economic growth in Cameroon using World Bank data and administrative data, with Sylvain Djatio, for ISSEA (Cameroon), Winter 2019.
- Head of the team in charge of designing the instruments (questionnaire, telephone application and others) for the survey on the perception and use of electronic transactions by the inhabitants of Yaoundé, for ISSEA, Winter 2019.
- Replication of Bedard and Deschenes (2005)'s paper: using 1960 IPUMS to analyze the impact of divorce
 on the economic status of women in the United States, for microenometric course with Adriana Bellou,
 University of Montreal, Winter 2021.
- Replication of the paper by Gu, Kelly, and Xiu (2020): Performance evaluation of several machine learning methods for the asset risk premia measurement problem, for time series course with Sílvia Gonçalves, McGill University, Winter 2021.
- Application of machine learning methods to bank telemarketing data in order to predict whether or not the client will subscribe a bank term deposit, for machine learning course with Russell Davidson, McGill University, Fall 2020.

Lecturer, University of Montreal

2021-present

- Economic Data Analysis (Undergraduate): Fall 2022;
- Mathematics for Economic Analysis (Undergraduate): Fall 2021 and Summer 2022.

Teaching assistant, University of Montreal

2020-present

- Advanced Econometrics (Ph.D.): Winter 2020, Winter 2021, and Winter 2023;
- Probability Theory for Economists (Ph.D.): Fall 2020;
- Mathematics for Economic Analysis (Undergraduate): Fall 2020, Fall 2021;
- Economics and Public Finance (Undergraduate): Winter 2021,
- Environment and natural resources (Undergraduate): Fall 2022.

Research in progress

2021-present

"Regularized CUE with many moment conditions", with Marine Carrasco;

Research areas

Econometric Theory (Inference with Many Instrumental Variables), Applied Econometrics, Causal Inference, and Machine Learning

Conference and presentations

- Quebec Social sciences PhD presentations group (Winter 2021 and 2023);
- 18th CIREQ Ph.D. Students' Conference (forthcoming, Summer 2023);
- 57th Annual Canadian Economics Association Meetings (forthcoming, Summer 2023);
- 62nd Annual Congress of Société canadienne de science économique (forthcoming, Summer 2023);
- 1st CIREQ Interdisciplinary PhD Student Conference on Big Data and Artificial Intelligence (forthcoming, Summer 2023).

Followships, honors, and awards

Ph.D. Fellowship, Department of Economics, University of Montreal	2019-present
Ph.D. Fellowship, CIREQ, University of Montreal	2019-present
Award of Excellence for the best student in Statistics, specializing in Statistical Modeling Applied to Finance and Insurance (M.Sc.), ISSEA, Cameroon	2018-2019
Best student in Statistics and Economics (M.Sc.), ISSEA, Cameroon	2016-2019
M.Sc. in Statistics Fellowship, Government of Cameroon	2016-2019
Best student in Mathematics (B.Sc.), University of Yaoundé	2015

Languages and programming skills

Languages: French (*Native*), English (*Advanced*)

Programming: Python (advanced), R, MATLAB, STATA.

Others: Microsoft (Word, Excel, Powerpoint), LATEX.